<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be inquired of in the Arch-deaconrie of Salop within the diocesse of Hereford, in the year 163[9?] at the visitation of Morgan Godwyn, Doctor of Lawes, Arch-deacon of Salop.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Archdeaconry of Salop.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00187</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10217.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1243</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21826211</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 21826211</idno>
            <idno type="VID">24910</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00187)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 24910)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1728:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be inquired of in the Arch-deaconrie of Salop within the diocesse of Hereford, in the year 163[9?] at the visitation of Morgan Godwyn, Doctor of Lawes, Arch-deacon of Salop.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Archdeaconry of Salop.</author>
                  <author>Godwyn, Morgan. fl. 1685</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Norton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>163[9?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:24910:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES TO BE INQVIRED OF IN THE ARCH-DEACONRIE of <hi>Salop,</hi> within the Dioceſſe of Hereford, in the yeare 163<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> At the Viſitation of <hi>Morgan Godwyn</hi> Doctor of Lawes, Arch-deacon of Salop.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by IOHN NORTON 163<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:24910:2"/>
            <head>The Tenor of the Oath, to bee Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to the Church-wardens, and Side-men.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou ſhall ſweare that you, and every of you, ſhall duly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and diligently inquire of all and every theſe Articles given you in charge; and that all affection, favor, hatred, malice, hope of reward and gaine, or feare of diſpleaſure ſet aſide; you ſhall preſent all and every ſuch perſon or perſons, that now is, or are, or of late hath or have bee<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> within your Pariſh, as hath or have committed any offence, or made any default mentioned in theſe or any of theſe Articles; or which are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently ſuſpected or defamed of any ſuch offence or default: wherein you ſhall deale uprightly and fully; neyther preſenting, nor ſparing to preſent any, contrary to truth: having in this action God before your eyes, with an ernest zeale to maintaine truth, and to ſuppreſſe vice: So helpe you God, and the holy contents of this Booke.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="query">
            <pb facs="tcp:24910:2"/>
            <head>Firſt concerning the Church, the Furniture and Ornaments thereof, and the Church Poſſesſions.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Nprimis,</hi> Whether have you in your ſeverall Churches and Chappells, the whole Bible of the largeſt Volume and the laſt Tranſlation, the Booke of Common Prayer, the two Bookes of Homilies, Biſhop <hi>Jewell</hi> his apology and the forme of Prayer for the <hi>5.</hi> of <hi>November</hi> ſet forth by authority, all well and fairely bound? as alſo the Booke of <hi>Canons</hi> or <hi>Conſtitutions Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> as is commanded?</p>
            <p n="2">2 Whether have you in your Church or Chappell a Font of ſtone whole and cleane with a cover ſet up in the ancient uſuall place: a convenient and decent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion Table, with a Carpet of Silke or ſome other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſtuffe continually layd upon the ſame at the time of Divine Service, and a faire linnen cloth thereon at the time of the receiving of the holy Communion. And whether is the ſame Table placed in ſuch convenient ſort, as that the Miniſter may be beſt heard in his Prayer and Adminiſtration: and that the greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber may Communicate. And whether is it ſo uſed out of time of Divine Service, as is not agreeable to the holy uſe of it; as by ſitting on it, throwing Hats on it, writing on it; or is it abuſed to other prophane uſes: And are the Ten <hi>Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> ſet up at the Eaſt end of your Church or Chappell where the people may beſt ſee and read them, and other ſentences of holy Scripture written on the walls likewiſe for that purpoſe?</p>
            <p n="3">3 Whether are the afternoones Sermons in the ſeverall Pariſhes turned into <hi>Catechizing</hi> by <hi>Queſtion</hi> and <hi>Anſwer,</hi> according to the forme preſcribed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Booke of Common Prayer? and whether doth every Lecturer reade Divine Service according to the liturgy Printed by authority, in his Surplice and Hood, before the Lecture? And whether are his <hi>Majeſties</hi> inſtructions in all things duly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved?</p>
            <p n="4">4 Whether have you in your ſaid Church or Chappell, a convenient ſeate for your Miniſter to reade Service in, together with a comely Pulpet ſet up in a convenient place, with a decent Cloth or Cuſhion for the ſame, a comely large Surplice, a faire Communion Cup of Silver with a cover agreeable, a Flagon of Silver, Tyn, or Pewter to put the Wine in, whereby it may be put or ſet on the Communion Table at the time of the conſecrating or bleſſing thereof, with all other things and Ornaments neceſſary for the celebration of Divine Service, and the Adminiſtration of the Sacraments? And whether have you a ſtrong Cheſt for the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>s for the poore, with three Locks and Keyes; and another Cheſt for keeping the <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ookes and Orn<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ments of the Church, and the regiſter Booke? And whether have you a regiſter Booke in parchment for Chriſtnings, Weddings,
<pb facs="tcp:24910:3"/>
and Burialls, and the ſame kept in all points according to the <hi>Canon</hi> in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe provided? And is the Mothers Chriſtian name therein regiſtred as well as the Fathers, and a tranſcript thereof brought in yearely, within one moneth after the <hi>25.</hi> of <hi>March</hi> in to the Lord Biſhops principall Regiſter? And whether have you in your ſaid Church or Chancell a Table ſet of the degres, wherein by Law are prohibited to marry?</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Whether is your Church or Chappell with the Chancell thereof, and your Parſonage or Vicaridge houſe, your Pariſh Almes-houſe and Church-houſe in good reparation: are they imployed to godly and their right holy uſes? Is your Church, Chancell, and Chappell decently and comely kept as well within as without, well tyled, well glazed, well paved, and the ſeates well mainteined according to the <hi>85. Canon</hi> in that behalfe provided? Or have any Patrons or others decayed the Parſonage Houſes, and kept a ſtipendiarie Preiſt or Curate in place where an Incumbent ſhould bee poſſeſſed? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is your Church-yard well fenced with Walls, Rayles, or Pales, and by whom: and if not, in whoſe default the ſame is, and what the defect or fault is? And whether any perſon have incroached on the ground of the Church-yard, or whether any perſon or perſons have uſed any thing or place conſecrated to holy uſe, prophanely or wickedly? Is your Church-yard well and orderly kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out abuſe? And is the whole conſecrated ground kept as becommeth the place ſo dedicated free from ſoile and all other naſtines, as piſſing againſt the Church, and defiling the Church-yard with their excrements and the like? And are the Bones of the dead decently interred or layd up in ſome fit place as beſeemeth Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> Whether have any ancient Monuments or glaſſe windowes béen defaced, or any braſſe Inſcriptions, Lead, Stones, Bells or any thing els belonging to your Church or Chappell been at any time purloyned, and by whom?</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> What Legacies have been given to the uſe and benefit of your Church, and how have they been beſtowed? Who hath received and detaineth them without due imployment? and whether doth any with-hold the ſtocke of the Church, or any goods or things given to good and charitable uſes.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> It there any in the Pariſh, that hath or doth refuſe to contribute towards the reparation of your Church, and toward the proviſion of ſuch things as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long thereunto?</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9</hi> Whether doth any private man or men of his or their owne authority erect any Pewes or built any ſeates in your Church, and what Pewes or ſeates have been ſo built, by whoſe procurement, and by whoſe authority?</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10</hi> Whether hath any Popiſh Recuſant being lawfully excommunicate, or any other excommunicated perſon, been interred or buried in your Church, or Church-yard, before abſolution from that cenſure and excommunication obteined? if yea, then by whom and when?</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11</hi> Whether have you a true Terrier of all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Glebe-lands, Medowes, Gardens, Orchards, Houſes, Stockes, Implements, Tenements, and Portions of Tythes, whether within your Pariſh or without belonging to your Parſonage or Vicarage taken by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> view of honeſt men in the ſaid Pariſh? and whether is it ſafely kept
<pb facs="tcp:24910:3"/>
and preſerved and in whoſe hands? and whether hath there a true Copy thereof, under the hands of the Miniſter and Church-wardens, been tranſmitted and layd up in the Biſhops Regiſtry, there to continue for a perpetuall memory thereof? And if you have no ſuch Terrier yet made, you the Church-wardens and Side<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men together with your Parſon or Vicar, or in his abſence, your Curate, are to make diligent enquiry of the Premiſes, and to make, ſubſcribe, and ſigne the ſaid Terrier, and to bring in a true copy of it into the Byſhops Reſtiſtry, as is afore ſayd.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="query">
            <head>Second Concerning the Clergy.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> VVHether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate diſtinctly and reverently ſay Divine Service upon Sundayes and Holy-dayes and other days appointed to be obſerved by the Booke of Common Prayer, as the Converſion of S. <hi>Paul.</hi> S. <hi>Barnabas</hi> day, Wedneſdayes and Frydayes, &amp; the Eves of every Sunday and Holy-day, at fit and uſuall times? And doth he duly obſerve the Orders, rits and ceremonies preſcribed in the ſaid Booke of Common Prayer, as will in rea,ding publique Prayers and the Litanie, as alſo in adminiſtring the Sacraments-Solemnization of Matrimony, viſiting the ſicke, burying the dead, Churching of we<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and other the like Rits, and Offices of the Church, in ſuch manner and forme as in the ſaid Booke of Common Prayer he is injoyned, without any omiſſion or addition? And doth he read the Booke of the laſt <hi>Canons</hi> yearely, and weare a Surplice according to the ſayd <hi>Canons?</hi> And if he be a graduate, whether doth he alſo weare upon his Surplice ſuch a hood as by the order of the Vniverſity is ſutable to his degree?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> whether have you any Lecture in your Pariſh? If yea, whether doth he twiſe at the leſt every yeere read himſelfe Divine Service, both Morning and Evening two ſeverall Sundayes, publiquely in his Surplice with an Hood theron anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to his degree of ſchoole; and alſo twiſe in the yeere adminiſter both Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. with ſuch Rites and Ceremonies as are preſcribed by the Booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer? Alſo, whether doth he read Divine Service according to the Liturgy Printed by authority, in his Surplice and Hood before his Lecture, according to his Maieſtyes late directions? whether doth he at any time preach in his Cloke, and not in his Gowne? whether doth your Preacher or Lecturer behave himſelfe in his Sermons and Lectures as he ought to doe, teaching obedience, and edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his auditorie in matters of Faith and good life, without intermedling with matters of State or other diſcourſe not fit for the Pulpit?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Whether have you any Lecture of Combination ſet up in your Pariſh? if yea, whether is it read by a company of grave and <hi>Orthodox</hi> Divines neer adioyning, and in the ſame Dioceſſe? and whether doe they preach in Gownes and not in Clokes?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate bid Holy-dayes and faſting-dayes as by the Booke of Common prayer is appoynted? And doth he give wa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>gs before hand to he Pariſhoners for the receiving the Holy Communion, as the <hi>22 Canon</hi> requireth? And whether doth he adminiſter the Holy Communion as often, and at ſuch times as that every Pariſhioner may receive the ſame at
<pb facs="tcp:24910:4"/>
the leaſt thrice in every yeare, whereof once at <hi>Eaſter?</hi> And whether doth your Miniſter receive the ſame himſelfe on every day, that he Adminiſters it to others, and uſe the words of inſtitution according to the Booke at every time the Bread and Wine is renued, according to the <hi>Proviſo</hi> of the <hi>21. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non?</hi> And doth he deliver the Bread and Wine to every Communicant ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and kneeling.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate before the ſeverall times of the Adminiſtration of the Lord's Supper, admoniſh and exhort his Pariſhioners, if any of them have their conſciences troubled and diſquieted, to reſort to him, or to ſome other learned Miniſter, and open their greife, that they may receive ſuch Ghoſtly counſell and comfort, as their conſcience may be releived, and by the Miniſter they may have the benefit of abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the quiet of their conſcience and avoidance of Scruple? And if any man confeſſe his ſecret or hidden ſinnes being ſicke or whole, to the Miniſter, for the unbarthening of his conſcience and receiving of ſpirituall conſolation of minde from him, doth he the ſaid Prieſt or Miniſter, or hath hee at any time revealed and made knowne to any perſon whatſoever, any crime or offence ſo committed to his truſt and ſecrecie, contrarie to the <hi>113. Canon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> Whether hath your Miniſter admitted to the holy Communion any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious offender or Schiſmatick, contrary to the <hi>26.</hi> and <hi>27. Canon?</hi> or hath he received any to the Communion being not of his owne cure? or hath he put any from the Communion, who are not publikely infamous for any notorious crime? doth he alway uſe and never omit the ſigne of the Croſſe in Baptiſme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or doth he Baptiſe in any Baſon, or other Veſſell, and not in the uſuall Font, or admit any Father to be God-father, or Mother to be God-mother to their owne children, or ſuch to be God-fathers and God-mothers who have not received the holy Communion; or Baptiſe any children that were not borne in the Pariſh, or wilfully refuſe to Baptiſe any Infant in his Pariſh, being in danger, having beene informed of the weaknes of the ſaid child: and whether the child dieth without Baptiſme through his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault?</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> Doth he refuſe to interre any which ought to bee interred in Chriſtian buriall, or defer the ſame longer then he ſhould; or bury any in Chriſtian buriall, which by the <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or Law of the Land, ought not to be ſo interred?</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> Whether hath your Miniſter Married any without a King, or without Banes publiſhed three ſeverall Sundayes or holy-dayes in time of Divine Service, in the ſeverall Churches or Chappells of their ſeverall above, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Booke of Common Prayer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or in times prohibited albeit the Banes were thrice publiſhed, without a Licence or diſpenſation from the Lord Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Herford,</hi> or his Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, firſt obteined in that behalfe? Or not betweene the houres of <hi>8.</hi> and <hi>12.</hi> in the Fore-noone, or have Married any in private houſes; or if the parties or eyther of them be under the age of <hi>21.</hi> yeeres, before their Parents
<pb facs="tcp:24910:4"/>
or Governours have ſignified their conſent unto him?</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9.</hi> Is your Miniſter a Preacher allowed? If yea, then by whom? If not, whether doth hee procure ſome who are lawfully licenſed, to preach monthly amongſt you at the leaſt?</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10.</hi> Doth your Miniſter (being licenſed) preach uſually according to the <hi>Canons,</hi> either in his own Cure, or in ſome other Church or Chappel neer adjoyning, where no other Preacher is, and how often hath he been negligent in that behalf, &amp; doth he preach ſtanding and with his hat off. Or whether doth he or his Curate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every Sunday when there is no Sermon, read an <hi>Homily</hi> or ſome part therof according as he ought to doe? or in caſe he be not licenſed to preach, doth hee take upon him to preach or expound the Scriptures in his owne Cure, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where? If ſo, then you are to preſent the ſame, the time and place, when and where he did it.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11</hi> Doth your Miniſter uſe to pray for the Kings Majeſty King Charles, and for the Queenes Majeſty, for Prince <hi>Charles</hi> his Highneſſe, &amp; all the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Progeny, with addition of ſuch ſtile and titles as are due to his <hi>Maieſty,</hi> and exhort the people to obedience to his <hi>Maieſty,</hi> and to al Magiſtrates in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity under him? And doth he alſo pray for all Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, and other Eccleſiaſticall perſons?</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12</hi> Doth your Miniſter, Preacher or Lecturer obſerve the forme of Prayer (and no other) before his or their Sermons, that is preſcribed by the <hi>55 Canon,</hi> therein moving the people as they are there directed, to joyne with him in Prayer for Chriſts holy Catholike Church, and for the Kings moſt excellent <hi>Maieſty,</hi> the Queene, the Prince, and the reſt of the Royall Progeny, Clergy and Councell, as in the <hi>Canon</hi> is required, alway concluding with the Lords Prayer?</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13</hi> Is your Miniſter continually reſident upon his benifice, or how long time hath he been abſent? And in caſe he be licenſed to be abſent, whether doth he cauſe his Cure to be ſufficiently ſupplyed according to the <hi>Canon?</hi> or in caſe he hath another benifice, Whether doth he ſupply his abſence by a Curate ſufficiently licenſed to preach in that Cure, where he himſelfe is not reſident? or otherwiſe, in caſe the ſmalneſſe of the living cannot finde a preaching Miniſter, doth he preach at both his Benifices uſually.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14</hi> Doth your Miniſter or Curat ſerve any more Cures then one? If yea, then what other Cure doth he ſerve: and how far are they diſtant?</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15</hi> Doth your Miniſter or Curate every Sunday and Holyday, before Evening prayer, for halfe an hower or more, examine and inſtruct the youth and ignorant perſons of his pariſh, in the tenn Commandements, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Creede, and in the Lords prayer, and the Sacraments accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as is preſcribed in the Catechiſme ſet forth in the Booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer only? And if he do not, where is the fault, either in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Maſters of the Children, or in the Curat neglecting his duty? And is he carefull to tender all ſuch youth of his pariſh as have been well inſtructed in their Catechiſme, to be confirmed by the Biſhop in his Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or any other time, as is appoynted by the Booke aforeſaid?</p>
            <p n="16">
               <pb facs="tcp:24910:5"/>
               <hi>16</hi> Doth your Miniſter in the Rogation dayes goe in perambulation of the Circuit of the Pariſh, ſaying and uſing the prayers, Suffrages, and Thankeſgiving to GOD, appoynted by Law according fo his duty, thanking GOD for his bleſſings, if there be plenty on the earth: or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to pray for his Grace and favor, if there be a feare of Scarſity?</p>
            <p n="17">
               <hi>17</hi> Hath your Miniſter admitted any Woman, begotten with child in Adultery or Fornication, to bee churched without Licence of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie?</p>
            <p n="18">
               <hi>18</hi> Hath your Miniſter or any other Preacher, baptized children, Churched any woman, or miniſtred the holy Communion in any private houſe, otherwiſe than by Law is allowed?</p>
            <p n="19">
               <hi>19.</hi> Whether have there beene any Children baptized in private houſes, by any perſon, or Midwife, or Popiſh Prieſt? and have ſuch Children thus pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately baptized, and ſurviving, been afterwards brought to your Church, to the intent the Congregation and the Miniſter of the Pariſh (in caſe they were not baptized by him) may be certified whether they, or any of them were lawfully bapt<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>zed or no?</p>
            <p n="20">
               <hi>20</hi> Whether have the children that have beene borne to any popiſh Recuſant or Recuſants in your Pariſh, beene publiquely baptized in your pariſh-Church, by your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate? or by whom elſe were they baptized, or where to your knowledge?</p>
            <p n="21">
               <hi>21</hi> Doth your Miniſter endeavour and labour diligently to reclaime the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Recuſants in his pariſh from their errors (if there be any ſuch abiding in your Pariſh?) Or whether is your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate over-converſant with, or a favourer of Recuſants, whereby he is ſuſpected not to bee ſincere in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?</p>
            <p n="22">
               <hi>22</hi> Hath your Miniſter taken upon him to appoint any publique or private Faſts, Prophecies or Exerciſes not approved by Law, or publique Authority; or hath uſed to meet in any private houſe or place with any perſon or perſons, there to conſult how to impeach or deprave the Booke of Common Prayer, or the Doctrine or Diſcipline of the Church of England? If yea, then you ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them all.</p>
            <p n="23">
               <hi>23</hi> Doth your Miniſter or Lecturer either in time of publique allowed Faſts, or at any other time, uſually deteine the Aſſembly or Congregation with Sermons longer than a full hower? If yea, then you ſhall preſent the time and place.</p>
            <p n="24">
               <hi>24</hi> Whether hath your Miniſter been preſent at any private conventicle, to conſult there of any courſe to bee taken by them, or by another upon their motion, which may any way tend to the impeachment or depraving of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of England, or of the booke of Common Prayer, or of any part of the Governement and Diſcipline now eſtabliſhed in the Church of England?</p>
            <p n="25">
               <hi>25</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter publiſh in his Sermons any Doctrine which is new and ſtrange, and diſagreeing from the Word of God, and from the Articles of Chriſtian Faith and Religion, agreed on and publiſhed <hi>Anno Dom.
<pb facs="tcp:24910:5"/>
1562.</hi> And whether doth hee teach any thing which hee would the people religiouſly to obſerve and beleeve, but that which is agreeable to the Scriptures, and that which the Catholique Fathers and ancient Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops have gathered out of that Doctrine according to the <hi>Canon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">
               <hi>26</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter in his Sermons enter into and handle any points of controverſie, contrarie to his Maieſties directions? whether doth hee, or any other Preacher in your pulpit particularly impugne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute any Doctrine delivered by any other Preacher in the ſame Church, or in any Church neere adioyning, before hee hath acquainted the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe therewith, and received order from him what to doe in that caſe?</p>
            <p n="27">
               <hi>27</hi> Hath your Miniſter ſtayed the publication of any excommunications or ſuſpenſions, or doth hee every halfe yeare denounce in his pariſh Church, all ſuch of his Pariſh as are excommunicated, and perſevere therein without ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to be abſolved, or doth hee wittingly and willingly keepe companie with ſuch as are excommunicate? and hath he admitted into your Church any perſon excommunicated, without a certificate of his abſolution from the Ordinary or other competent Iudge?</p>
            <p n="28">
               <hi>28</hi> Doth your Miniſter carefully looke to the reliefe of the poore, and from time to time call upon his Pariſhioners to give ſomewhat as they can ſpare, to godly and charitable uſes, eſpecially when they make their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments?</p>
            <p n="29">
               <hi>29</hi> Doth your Miniſter or Curate reſort unto ſuch as be dangerouſly ſicke in your Pariſh, to inſtruct and comfort them in their diſtreſſes, according to the order of the booke of Common Prayer: not omitting, then eſpecially, to move them earneſtly to liberality toward the poore?</p>
            <p n="30">
               <hi>30</hi> Whether doth your Miniſter, or any, having taken holy Orders, being now ſilenced or ſuſpended, or any other perſon of your knowledge, or as you have heard, hold any conventicles, or doth preach in any place, or doth uſe any other forme of Divine Service than is appointed in the Booke of Common Prayer? If yea, then you are to preſent their names, and with whom?</p>
            <p n="31">
               <hi>31</hi> Whether is your Curate licenced to ſerve by the Biſhop of this Dioces, or by any other, and by whom?</p>
            <p n="32">
               <hi>32</hi> Whether is there anie in your Pariſh, who having beene admitted into holie Orders, either Deacon or Miniſter, doth voluntarily relinquiſh and forſake his calling, and liveth in the courſe of his life as a meere Lay-man?</p>
            <p n="33">
               <hi>33</hi> Whether is your Miniſter ſtudious in holy Scripture, and abſtaineth from mechanicall trades or labour not befitting his function, and from apparrel unſeemely for his calling, uſing that decencie and gravity therein, as is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the <hi>47. Canon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="34">
               <hi>34</hi> Is your Miniſter noted or defamed to have obtained his Benefice or his Orders by ſimony, or any other way defamed to be a ſimoniacall perſon, or any way noted to be a Schiſmatique or ſchiſmatically affected, or reputed to be an incontinent perſon, or doth table or lodge any ſuch in his houſe: or is bee
<pb facs="tcp:24910:6"/>
a frequenter of Tavernes, Innes, or Ale-houſes, or any place ſuſpected for ill rule: Or is hee a common Drunkard, a common Gameſter, or play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at Dice, a Swearer, or one that applieth himſelfe not at his ſtudies, or is otherwiſe offenſive and ſcandalous to his Function or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="query">
            <head>Third, Concerning Schoole-Maſters, Phyſicians, Chirurgians, Mid-wives and Pariſh-Clerkes.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> DOth any in your Pariſh openly or privately take upon him to teach Schoole, without Licence of the Ordinarie, and is hee conformable to the Religion now eſtabliſhed? and doth hee bring his Schollars to the Church, to heare Divine Service and Sermons? and doth hee inſtruct his ſchollars in the grounds of the Religion now eſtabliſhed in the Church of England, and is hee carefull and diligent to benefit his ſchollers in learning?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Doth your Schoole-maſter tea<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h and inſtruct his youth in the Catechiſme allowed by authority, or in ſome other Catechiſme? if in ſome other, what is that Catechiſme that he ſo teacheth?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Is any Living or Meanes given towards the erection or maintenance of any Schoole with-holden backe, or otherwiſe imployed and by whom?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Doth any keepe Schoole in the Chancell or Church, by which meanes that holy place and the Communion Table are many waies profaned, and the windowes broken?</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> How many Phyſitians, Chirurgians, or Mid-wives have you in your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh? how long have they uſed their ſeverall ſciences or Offices, and by what Authority? and how have they demeaned themſelves therein? and of what ſkill are they accounted to be in their profeſſions?</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> Have you a fit Pariſh-Clerke, aged twentie yeares at leaſt, of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt life, able to reade and write? are his and the Sextons wages duly paied without fraud or diminution, according to the ancient cuſtome of your Pariſh? what is his wages? by whom is he choſen? whether is he approved by the Ordinarie? Is hee diligent in his Office, and ſerviceable to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? doth hee keepe the Church cleane and dores locked? Is there any thing loſt or ſpoyled through his default? and doth hee execute his Office duly?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="query">
            <head>Fourth, Concerning the Pariſhioners.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> VVHether any of your Pariſhioners, being ſixteen yeares of age or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, or others lodging or commonly reſorting to anie houſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Pariſh, doe wilfullie abſent themſelves from your Pariſh Church, upon Sundaies or Holi-daies, at morning and evening praiers? or who come late to Church, and depart from Church before Service be done upon the ſaid daies? or
<pb facs="tcp:24910:6"/>
who doe not reverently behave themſelves during the time b<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Divine Service, devoutly kneeling when the generall Confeſſion of ſins, the Letanie, the tenne Commandements, and all prayers and Collects are read, and uſing due and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reverence when the bleſſed Name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt is mentioned, and ſtanding up at each Creed, at the Goſpell, at each Glorie be to the Father. &amp;c. and at the <hi>Te Deum,</hi> according to the practiſe of his Maieſties Chappell Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, and of the Cathedrall Church of <hi>Hereford;</hi> or who doe cover their heads in the Church during the time of Divine Service, unleſſe it be in caſe of neceſſitie, in which caſe they may weare a night-cap or Coyf? or who doe give themſelves to babling, talking or walking, and are not attentive to heare the Word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched or read? whether any of your Pariſh being of <hi>16.</hi> yeares of age or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, doe not receive the holy Communion thrice every yeare, whereof once at Eaſter, and whether they doe not devoutly kneele at the receiving thereof? And whether any having divers houſes of remove, doe ſhift from place to place, of purpoſe to defeate the performance of their Chriſtian duties in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Whether any of your Pariſhioners being admoniſhed thereof, doe not ſend their children ſervants, and apprentiſes, to the Miniſter, to be catechiſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch Sundayes and Holy-dayes as are appointed? or whether any of them doe refuſe to come; or if they come, refuſe to learne thoſe inſtructions ſet forth in the Booke of Common Prayer?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Whether doe any of your Pariſh entertaine within their houſe, any ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iourner, common gueſts or other perſons, who refuſe to frequent Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or receave the holy Communion as aforeſaid? preſent their names, quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or conditions.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Whether doth any in your Pariſh under the degree of a Nobleman, or not thereto allowed by the Law, keepe in his houſe any Chaplaine? preſent their names.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> What Recuſant Papiſts have yee in your Pariſh, or other Sectaries? preſent their names, qualities or condition: whether they keepe any Schoole-maſter in their houſe, which commeth not to Church to heare Divine Service, and receive the holy Communion? what is his name, and how long hath hee taught there or elſewhere?</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> Whether any of the ſaid Popiſh Recuſants, or other ſchiſmatiques, doe la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſeduce and with-draw others from the Religion now eſtabliſhed? or inſtruct their families or children in Popiſh Religion; or reſuſe to entertaine any, eſpecially in place of greateſt ſervice or truſt but ſuch as concurre with them in their opinions?</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> How long have the ſaid Popiſh Recuſants abſtained from Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or from the Communion?</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> Is there any in your Pariſh, that reteine, ſell, utter or diſperſe any Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh bookes, or writings, or other bookes, Libraries, or writings of any Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, touching the Religion, State, or Governement Eccleſiaſticall of this Kingdome of England, or keepe any Manuments of ſuperſtition, uncancelled or undefaced?</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb facs="tcp:24910:7"/>
               <hi>9</hi> Whether have you any in your Pariſh, which heretofore being Popiſh Recuſants or Sectaries, have ſince reformed themſelves, and come to Church to heare Divine Service, and receive the Sacraments? If yea, then who are they? and how long ſince have they ſo reformed themſelves? and whether they ſtill remaine in their conformity?</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10</hi> Are there any in your Pariſh that refuſe to have their children baptized, or themſelves to receive the Communion at the hands of your Miniſter, taking exception againſt him, and what cauſes or exceptions doo they alledge; or have any married Wives refuſed to come to Church, according to the Booke of Common Prayer, to give God thankes after their Childbirth, for their ſafe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance? And whether doe any of or in your Pariſh, refuſe to have their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren baptized in your Pariſh Church, according to the forme preſcribed in the Booke of Common Prayer?</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11</hi> Do an<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of your Pariſh uſually goe to other Pariſh Churches to heare Div<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne Service or Sermons? Or doe they communicate, or baptize their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in any other Pariſh?</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12</hi> Whether be there any in your Pariſh, who will come to heare the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, but will not come to publique Prayers appointed in the Booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, making a ſchiſme or diviſion (as it were) betweene the uſe of publique Prayer and Preaching?</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13</hi> What perſons within your Pariſh for any offence, contumacie or crime of Eccleſiaſticall cogniſance doe ſtand excommunicate? preſent their names, and for what cauſe they doe ſtand excommunicated, and how long they have ſo ſtood, and what perſon or perſons doe wittingly and uſually keepe them company.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14</hi> Whether any, not being in Orders, doe execute any Prieſtly or Miniſteriall Office in your Church, Chappell, or Church-yard, and what bee their names?</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15</hi> Hath any perſon in your Pariſh quarrelled, or ſtricken, or uſed any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to your Miniſter, or hath ſtricken or quarrelled with any other perſon within your Church or Church-yard, or demeaned himſelfe diſorderly in the Church, by filthy or prophane talke, or any baſe or immodeſt behaviour? Or hath diſturbed the Miniſter in time of Divine Service or Sermon, or hath li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled, or ſpoken ſlanderous words againſt your Miniſter, to the ſcandall of his vocation, or defamed any of his neighbours touching any crime of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall cogniſance?</p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16</hi> Whether any of, or in your pariſh, without conſent of the Ordinarie, or other lawfull authority, have cauſed any to doe penance, or to be cenſured or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for any matter of Eccleſiaſticall cogniſance, by any Veſtry-meetings, or otherwiſe by their owne authority? or have taken any mony or commutation for the ſame? preſent their names that have done it, and who have beene ſo pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, in what manner, and upon what cauſe.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <hi>17</hi> Whether any perſon in your Pariſh do exerciſe any trade or labour, buy or ſell, or keepe open Shops or Ware-houſes upon any Sundaie or Holy-day, by themſelves, their ſervants, or Apprentiſes, or have otherwiſe prophaned the ſaid dayes, contrary to the Orders of the Church of England? And whether
<pb facs="tcp:24910:7"/>
there be any In-Kéepers, Ale-houſe-kéepers, Victuallers or other Perſons, that permit any Perſons in their Houſes, to eate, drinke, or play, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time of Divine Service or Sermon, or reading the <hi>Homilies</hi> in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone or afternoone, upon thoſe dayes?</p>
            <p n="18">
               <hi>18</hi> Whether is the <hi>5</hi> day of November kept Holy, and thankeſgiving made to God, for his <hi>Maieſty</hi> and this States happy deliverance, according to the Ordinance in that behalfe?</p>
            <p n="19">
               <hi>19</hi> Whether any of your Pariſh hold or frequent any Conventicles or private Congregations, or make or maintaine any Conſtitutions agreed upon in ſuch aſſemblies? Or any that doe write, or publiquely or privatly ſpeake againſt the Booke of Common Prayer, or any thing therein conteined, or againſt any of the <hi>Articles</hi> of Religion agreed upon in <hi>Anno 1562.</hi> Or againſt the <hi>Kings</hi> Supremacy in cauſes <hi>Eccleſiaſtique</hi> or againſt the Oath of Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, or of allegeance, as pretending the ſame to bee unlawfull, and not warrantable by Gods word? or againſt any of the Rites or Ceremonies of the Church of England, now eſtabliſhed? Or againſt the Governement of the Church of England under the Kings moſt excellent <hi>Majeſty,</hi> by Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Arch-deacons, Deanes, and other Officers of the ſame; affirming the ſame to be repugnant to the word of God, and that the ſaid Eccleſiaſticall Officers are not lawfully ordeined? Or whether there be any Authors, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorers, or maintainers of Hereſie or Schiſme, or that be ſuſpected to be A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts, Libertines, Browniſts, of the Family of Love, or of any other Hereſie or Schiſme? preſent their names.</p>
            <p n="20">
               <hi>20</hi> Whether have any in your Pariſh Married within the degrees by Law prohibited, and where, and by whom? And whether any couple in your Pariſh being Lawfully Married, live apart one from the other, without due ſeparation by the Law; or any that have beene Divorced, which keepe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with any other at Bed or at Board?</p>
            <p n="21">
               <hi>21</hi> Whether your Hoſpitalls and Almes-Houſes, and other ſuch Houſes and Corporations, founded to good and charitable uſes, and the Lands, Poſſeſſions and Goods of the ſame, bee ordered and diſpoſed of, as they ſhould be? And do the Maſters, Governors, Fellowes, and others of the ſaid Houſes and Corporations, behave and demeane themſelves according to the holy Ordinances and Statutes of their ſeverall Foundations?</p>
            <p n="22">
               <hi>22</hi> Whether have you any in your Pariſh to your knowledge, or by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fame or report, which have committed adultery, fornication or inceſt: or any which have impudently bragged or boaſted, that he or they have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved incontinently with any Perſon or Perſons whatſoever: or any that have attempted the chaſtitie of any woman, or ſolicited any woman to have the carnall knowledge of her bodie: or which are commonlie reputed to be common Drunkards, Blaſphemers of Gods holy Name, common ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, common ſlanderers of their Nighbours, and ſowers of diſcord, filthie and laſcivious Talkers, Vſurers, ſimoniacall perſons, Baudes, or Harborers of Women with child which be unmarried, or conveying or ſuffering them to go away before they have made ſatiſfaction to the Church, or anie that
<pb facs="tcp:24910:8"/>
having been heretofore preſented, or ſuſpected oſ any of the aforeſaid crimes, have for that cauſe departed your pariſh, and are now returned againe? Or any which have uſed any inchantments, Sorceries, Charmes, or witchcrafts, which are not made Felony by the Statutes of this Realme: Or any that have committed any perjury in any <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> Court in an <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> Cauſe, or which have committed any forgery puniſhable by the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> Laws; or any procurers or abettors of the ſaid offenſes: Ye ſhall truly preſent the names of all and ſingular the ſaid offenders, and with whom they have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſaid offenſes, in caſe they have not been publiquely puniſhed to your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for the ſaid crimes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="query">
            <head>Fiftly Touching the Church-wardens and Side-men.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> VVHether you, and the Church-wardens, Queſt-men, or Side-men from time to time do, and have done their diligence, in not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering any idle perſon to abide either in the Church-yard, or Church-porch, in Service or Sermon time, but cauſing them either to come into the Church to heare Divine Service, or to depart, and not to diſturbe ſuch as be hearers there? And whether they have, and you do diligently ſee the Pariſhioners duly reſort to the Church every Sunday and Holy-day, and there to remaine during Divine Service and Sermen? And whether you or your predeceſſors, Church-wardens there, ſuffer any Playes, Feaſts, Drinkings, or any other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaine uſages to bee kept in your Church, Chappell, or Church-yards, or have ſuffered any perſon or perſons, without reſtreining them to your and their uttermoſt power to be tipling or drinking in any Inne or victualling houſe, in your Pariſh, during the time of Divine Service and Sermons on Sundays and Holi-dayes?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Whether and how often have you admitted any to Preach within your Church or Chappell, who was not ſufficiently licenſed? And whether you toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with your Miniſter, have not taken diligent head and care, that every Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioner being of <hi>16</hi> yeares of age or upwards, have received thrice every yeare as aforeſaid: and alſo that no ſtranger have uſually come to your Church, from their owne Pariſh-Church?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> Whether have there been provided againſt every Communion, a ſufficient quantity of fine white Bread, and good and wholeſome Wine for the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants that ſhall receive? And whether that Wine be brought in a cleane and ſweet ſtanding Pot of Pewter, or ſome other purer metall?</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Whether were you choſen by the conſent of the Miniſter and the pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? And have the late Church-wardens given up a juſt accompt for their time, and delivered to their ſucceſſors by bill indented the money and other things b<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>longing to the Church, which was in their hands? And are the Almes of the Church faithfully diſtributed to the uſe of the poore?</p>
            <p n="5">5 Whether do you ſee the names of all Preachers, which are ſtrangers, and
<pb facs="tcp:24910:8"/>
do preach in your Pariſh-Churches, to be noted in a Booke for that purpoſe, and whether ev<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry Preacher do ſubſcribe his name, and of whom he had his Licence?</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> Whether any man do trouble or moleſt you for doing your duties?</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> Whether be there any Legacie given to the Church or poore people, or to <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e mending of high-wayes, or otherwiſe by the Teſtators, with holden? <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>n whoſe hands is it, by whom was it given, and by whom is it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olden?</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> Do you know of any other default or crime of <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> Cogniſance? <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>f yea, you are to preſent the ſame by vertue of your Oathes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THe Miniſter of every Pariſh may and ought to joyne in preſentment with the Church-wardens and Sidemen; and if they will not preſent, the Miniſter may and ought himſelfe to preſent the defaults and crimes aforeſaid: And there muſt bee ſeverall preſentments made to every ſeverall Article: and the Miniſter, Church-wardens and Sworne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are to meete and confer about the ſaid preſentments, and anſwering of every the aforeſaid Articles.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
